A Guide to the Administrative files of the Virginia Dept. of Motor Vehicles, 1941-1972
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Administrative files of the Virginia Dept. of Motor Vehicles, 1941-1972
The Library of Virginia
30469
68.95 cu. ft. (197 boxes)
Virginia. Dept. of Motor Vehicles.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Virginia Division of Motor Vehicles, 30 June 1979.
Biographical Information
On March 17, 1906, the General Assembly passed an act of giving the secretary of the commonwealth responsibility for motor vehicle registration and the issuance of drivers' licenses. The office of commissioner of motor vehicles was created by an act of the General Assembly passed on March 4, 1924, and assumed the duties concerning motor vehicles earlier undertaken by the secretary of the commonwealth, including the enforcement of motor vehicle laws.
The Division of Motor Vehicles was created within the Department of Taxation by the state government reorganization act passed on April 18, 1927. The General Assembly passed an act on March 26, 1932, that consolidated all existing motor vehicle laws and placed the Division of Motor Vehicles under the Department of Finance (which existed only on paper). The division yielded its law enforcement duties to the Department of State Police when that agency was created on March 14, 1942. The reorganization of state government authorized by the General Assembly on March 30, 1948, established the Division of Motor Vehicles as an independent state agency.
The division was placed under the secretary of transportation and public safety on April 8, 1972. The General Assembly created separate secretariats for transportation and for public safety on April 12, 1976, and placed the division under the secretary of transportation. Effective July 1, 1984, the secretariats of transportation and public safety again were combined.
The Division of Motor Vehicles exercises authority over motor vehicle registration as well as the licensing of motor vehicle operators. The division also licenses motor vehicle dealers, collects taxes on gasoline and other fuels, and promotes motor vehicle safety. Departments that function under the administration of the Commissioner of Motor Vehicles are the Bureau of Registration and Title Records, Contracts and Real Estate Administration, Fiscal Affairs, Management Information Systems, and Physical Plant. Genre
Scope and Content
Administrative files, 1941-1972, of the Virginia Department of Motor Vehicles. The collection is housed in 197 boxes and includes administrative files, building files, clippings, correspondence, and general ledgers. The collection is arranged into six series, Series I: Papers of G.W. James, Executive Assistant to the Commissioner and Publicity Director; Series II: General Ledgers; Series III: Correspondence of the Commissioner of the D.M.V.; Records of Buildings, Operations and Maintenance; Papers of W.B. Henshaw, Director of the Bureau of Registration and Title Records; and Papers of the Commissioner of D.M.V.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Papers of G.W. James, Executive Assistant to the Commissioner and Publicity Director, ca. 1941-1960
Series II: General Ledgers, 1949-1964
Series III: Correspondence of the Commissioner of the D.M.V., 1963-1969
Series IV: Records of Buildings, Operations and Maintenance, 1950-1964
Series V: Papers of W.B. Henshaw, Director of the Bureau of Registration and Title Records, 1960-1972
Series VI: Papers of the Commissioner of D.M.V., 1941-1962.
Contents List
- Series I: Papers of G.W. James, Executive Assistant to the Commissioner and Publicity Director, ca. 1941-1960, Extent: 11.55 cu. ft. (7 boxes). (Box 1-33)
  - Correspondence and Information Files, 1943-1959 (Box 1-17)
  - History, 1936-1952 (Box 18-19)
  - Clippings, 1952 (Box 20)
  - Clippings, 1953 (Box 21)
  - Clippings, 1953-1954 (Box 22)
  - Clippings, 1954 (Box 23)
  - Clippings, 1955 (Box 24)
  - Clippings, 1956 (Box 25)
  - Clippings, 1957-1958 (Box 26)
  - Clippings, 1959 (Box 27)
  - Press Relations & Publications, 1942-1947 (Box 28-29)
  - Correspondence and Information Files, 1941-1953 (Box 30)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1949 (Box 31)
  - Correspondence, 1948-1949 (Box 32)
  - Correspondence and Annual Reports, 1943-1949 (Box 33)
- Series II: General Ledgers, 1949-1964, Extent: 9.8 cu. ft. (28 boxes). (Box 34-61)
  - General Ledgers, 1958-1959 (Box 34)
  - General Ledgers, 1963 (Box 35)
  - General Ledgers, 1962 (Box 36)
  - General Ledgers, 1961 (Box 37)
  - General Ledgers, 1960 (Box 38)
  - General Ledgers, 1959 (Box 39)
  - General Ledgers, 1958 (Box 40)
  - General Ledgers, Revenue Ledgers, 1963 (Box 41)
  - General Ledgers, Revenue Ledgers, 1958-1962 (Box 42)
  - General Ledgers, Classified Ledgers, 1964 (Box 43)
  - General Ledgers, Accounts Receivable, 1963 (Box 44)
  - General Ledgers, Accounts Receivable, 1962 (Box 45)
  - General Ledgers, Accounts Receivable, 1961 (Box 46)
  - General Ledgers, Accounts Receivable, 1960 (Box 47)
  - General Ledgers, Accounts Receivable, 1959 (Box 48)
  - General Ledgers, Accounts Receivable, 1958 (Box 49)
  - General Ledgers, Accounts Receivable, 1965 (Box 50)
  - General Ledgers, Accounts Receivable, 1965 (Box 51)
  - General Ledgers, Interstate Bus Lines Accounts, 1960 (Box 52)
  - General Ledgers, Classified Ledgers, 1965 (Box 53)
  - General Ledgers, Interstate Bus Lines Accounts, 1964 (Box 54)
  - General Ledgers, Interstate Bus Lines Accounts, 1963 (Box 55)
  - General Ledgers, Accounts Receivable, 1964 (Box 56)
  - General Ledgers, Accounts Receivable (Box 57)
  - General Ledgers, Expense Ledgers, 1955-1958 (Box 58)
  - General Ledgers, Expense Ledgers, 1953-1955 (Box 59)
  - General Ledgers, Expense Ledgers, 1951-1953 (Box 60)
  - General Ledgers, Expense Ledgers, 1949-1951 (Box 61)
- Series III: Correspondence of the Commissioner of the D.M.V., 1963-1969, Extent: 1.75 cu. ft. (5 boxes). (Box 62-66)
  - Correspondence, 1963-1966 (Box 62)
  - Correspondence, 1966-1968 (Box 63)
  - Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 64)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1964 (Box 65)
  - Highway Study Commission, Continuous Files, 1962 (Box 66)
- Series IV: Records of Buildings, Operations and Maintenance, 1950-1964, Extent: 1.75 cu. ft. (5 boxes). (Box 67-71)
  - Physical Plant Files, 1950-1964 (Box 67)
  - Physical Plant Files, 1957-1964 (Box 68)
  - Physical Plant Files, 1946-1957 (Box 69)
  - Physical Plant Files, 1948-1949 (Box 70)
  - Physical Plant Files, Audit Files, 1958-1969 (Box 71)
- Series V: Papers of W.B. Henshaw, Director of the Bureau of Registration and Title Records, 1960-1972, Extent: 4.9 cu. ft. (14 boxes). (Box 72-85)
  - Audit Files - Administration Files (A), 1968-1970 (Box 72)
  - Administration Files (A), 1969-1972 (Box 73)
  - Audit Files - Administration Files (B), 1965-1969 (Box 74)
  - Administration Files (B), 1965-1969 (Box 75)
  - Administration Files (Budget Requests), 1968-1970 (Box 76)
  - Administration Files (B), 1968-1972 (Box 77)
  - Administration Files (B-C), 1966-1970 (Box 78)
  - Administration Files (C), 1968-1970 (Box 79)
  - Administration Files (C-D), 1965-1969 (Box 80)
  - Administration Files (D-I), 1968-1970 (Box 81)
  - Administration Files (I), 1954-1970 (Box 82)
  - Administration Files (I-L), 1964-1968 (Box 83)
  - Administration Files (M-S), 1968-1970 (Box 84)
  - Administration Files (S-W), 1968-1970 (Box 85)
- Series VI: Papers of the Commissioner of D.M.V., 1941-1962, Extent: 39.2 cu. ft. (112 boxes). (Box 86-197)
  - MVSR Act, 1944-1951 (Box 86)
  - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 87)
  - Correspondence, 1944-1953 (Box 88)
  - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 89)
  - Correspondence, 1952-1953 (Box 90)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1953 (Box 91)
  - Correspondence, 1941-1953 (Box 92)
  - Correspondence, 1943, 1953 (Box 93)
  - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 94)
  - Correspondence, 1945, 1954 (Box 95)
  - Correspondence, 1946, 1954 (Box 96)
  - Correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box 97)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1953 (Box 98)
  - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 99)
  - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 100)
  - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 101)
  - Manuals, 1960-1969 (Box 102-104)
  - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 105-110)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1955 (Box 111-113)
  - Correspondence, 1955 (Box 114-119)
  - Correspondence, 1955-1956 (Box 120)
  - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 121-122)
  - Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 123)
  - Correspondence, 1956-1958 (Box 124-127)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box 128-129)
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 130)
  - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 131-135)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1944, 1952, 1959 (Box 136)
  - Correspondence, 1942, 1948 (Box 137)
  - Correspondence, 1941, 1959 (Box 138)
  - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 139-140)
  - Correspondence, 1945-1951 (Box 141)
  - Correspondence, 1945-1950 (Box 142)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 143-145)
  - Correspondence, 1951, 1962 (Box 146-148)
  - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 149)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1963 (Box 150)
  - Correspondence, 1952, 1962 (Box 151)
  - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 152)
  - Correspondence, 1943, 1952, 1962 (Box 153)
  - Correspondence, 1941, 1948, 1952 (Box 154)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1948 (Box 155)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1952 (Box 156)
  - Correspondence, 1941-1948 (Box 157)
  - Correspondence, 1945-1959 (Box 158)
  - Correspondence, 1948-1952 (Box 159)
  - Correspondence, 1941-1952 (Box 160)
  - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 161)
  - Correspondence, 1944, 1957 (Box 162)
  - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 163)
  - Correspondence, 1952, 1957 (Box 164-168)
  - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 169)
  - Correspondence, 1952, 1957 (Box 170-171)
  - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 172-173)
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 174-175)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1960 (Box 176)
  - Correspondence, 1951, 1958 (Box 177)
  - Correspondence, 1958, 1960 (Box 178-180)
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 181)
  - Correspondence, 1958, 1960 (Box 182)
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 183)
  - Correspondence, 1951, 1960 (Box 184)
  - Correspondence, 1951, 1960-1961 (Box 185)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1951, 1961 (Box 186)
  - Correspondence, 1951, 1961 (Box 187)
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 188)
  - Correspondence, 1951, 1961 (Box 189-192)
  - Correspondence, 1961-1962 (Box 193)
  - Correspondence, 1951, 1961 (Box 194)
  - Correspondence, 1951, 1961-1962 (Box 195)
  - Correspondence, 1962 (Box 196-197)